<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Özgür Asar, PhD</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Özgür Asar, PhD</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussian Modelling</title>
      <link>/project/non-gaussian-modelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/non-gaussian-modelling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project consists of a number of methodological works of linear mixed-effects models and joint modelling of longitudinal and time-to-event outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;linear-mixed-effects-models&#34;&gt;Linear-Mixed Effects Models&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/bimj.201500270&#34;&gt;Asar et al. (2016)&lt;/a&gt; we consider a linear mixed-effects model that assumes observed outcomes are underlying signal plus additive noise. Underlying signal is de-composed as fixed-effects, time-invariant 
random-effects, a stochastic process. We assume a multivariate t distribution for the repeated outcomes of a specific subject. The R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/lmenssp/index.html&#34;&gt;lmenssp&lt;/a&gt; implements the methods. The methodology improves on the widely used multivariate Gaussian model, yet it has some drawbacks due to formulating the t distribution with a single mixing variable for a specific subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1804.02592&#34;&gt;Asar et al.(2019a)&lt;/a&gt; we de-coupled the mixing varible and proposed a computationally efficient algorithm for maximum likelihood inference especially to analyse tall data-sets, i.e. data-sets with many rows. De-coupling allows us dropping the dependence between the random terms of the model. The R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://bitbucket.org/davidbolin/ngme/src/default/&#34;&gt;ngme&lt;/a&gt; implements the proposed methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;joint-modelling-of-longitudinal-and-time-to-event-outcomes&#34;&gt;Joint Modelling of Longitudinal and Time-to-Event Outcomes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.00816&#34;&gt;Asar et al.(2019b)&lt;/a&gt; we considered joint modelling of longitudinal and survival outcomes with t distributed random-effects and error terms. 
Random-effects and error terms were assumed to be independent and error terms were assumed to be serially indpendent. To the best of our knowledge this is the first work that proposed such a flexible joint model. The R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ozgurasarstat/robjm&#34;&gt;robjm&lt;/a&gt; implements the methods for modelling and dynamic predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Asar et al.(2019c)&lt;/a&gt; we further extend the model of &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.00816&#34;&gt;Asar et al.(2019b)&lt;/a&gt; by allowing the degrees-of-freedom and scale parameters of the t distribution for the error term being time-varying. 
This is a likely scenario where data have different frequencies of outliers through time. 
Related methods are also implemented in the R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ozgurasarstat/robjm&#34;&gt;robjm&lt;/a&gt;. 
This work is nearly finished and will be available from arXiv soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time monitoring</title>
      <link>/project/real-time-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/real-time-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project contains a number of works mainly applied to kidney failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;incipient-renal-failure&#34;&gt;Incipient Renal Failure&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/biostatistics/article/16/3/522/269574&#34;&gt;Diggle, Sousa and Asar (2015)&lt;/a&gt; we considered 
modelling 392,870 estimated glomerular filtration 
rate (eGFR) observations from 22,910 patients living in the city of Salford in Greater 
Manchester. The model is a linear mixed-effects model with a Gaussian process term for long series of repeated measurement data. The aim is to identify high risk primary care patient in order for timely referral to secondary care. We base our methods on a clinical guideline 
that says a primary care patient should be referred to secondary care if s/he loses 
kidney functon at least at a rate of 5% per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;predicting-kidney-graft-survival&#34;&gt;Predicting Kidney Graft Survival&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.00816&#34;&gt;Asar, Fournier and Dantan (2019)&lt;/a&gt; we predict kidney graft survival for patients in the French transplant cohort, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.divat.fr/en&#34;&gt;DIVAT&lt;/a&gt;. The model is a joint model for longitudinal and 
survival data with non-Gaussian random-effects and measurement error term. 
We propose improved predictions of kidney graft survival compared to the 
model with Gaussian terms that was proposed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/ndt/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/ndt/gfz027/5374746&#34;&gt;Fournier et al.(2019)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Software</title>
      <link>/project/statistical-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/statistical-software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project describes the statistical software that have been prepared o implement the methodologies we developed. So far all the software are in the R platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lmenssp&#34;&gt;lmenssp&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;robjm&#34;&gt;robjm&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;mmm--mmm2&#34;&gt;mmm &amp;amp; mmm2&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;pnmtrem&#34;&gt;pnmtrem&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
